This week we're going to talk about array formulas,
这周我们来谈谈 数组公式 ，
let's have a look at the example of this week, where we
让我们来看看本周的例子，
are looking at exam results for a teacher.
这是一份整理给老师看的学生考试成绩。
We interrupt this recording for an important message about Types
我们先中断一下，来谈谈关于”类型”的一些重要知识
Today we're going to talk about
今天我们要谈谈
type theory, because it's super important in order for us to be able to understand
关于“类型”的理论，因为它对我们理解
this week's material.
本周的材料至关重要。
So we're going to start really really basic, so don't worry.
我们会从基础开始，所以不用担心。
This is easy, right?
这很容易，是不是？
2 plus 3 is 5, but these are not just numbers. They also have the type
2加3等于5，但这些 不仅仅是数字而已。 它们的“类型”也是数字，
of being a number and I'm going to
现在我要
annotate all types with a different colour. So what we're calculating here
把所有不同的“类型”用不同颜色标注。 我们正在计算的
is a number and a number
是一个数字加上一个数字
result in a number. But this is not how we write formulas in Excel, we can write
得到另外一个数字。 但我们并不是在Excel里这样写公式的，
numbers
我们可以把数字直接写在公式中
in a formula, but we can also use cells. So let's have a look
但是我们还可以使用单元格来写公式。 现在让我们来看看
at how that looks.
它们到底是怎么样的。
So we have these two cells in a spreadsheet and we can say A1
在我们的电子表格中，我们有这两个单元格，
plus A2 in this case
我们可以说，在这个情况下，
is also 5. So what are the types here?
A1加A2的等于5。 那么，这些是属于什么“类型”呢？
Well 5 is a number, that's easy. But A1 is not a number,
5是一个数字，这很简单简单。 但 A1却不是一个数字，
it's a cell, it's a reference to a number
这是一个单元格，它是一个数字的引用
so let's draw it like this
让我们可以这样说
and say something that contains a number and
如果要把两个含有数字的东西相加
something that contains a number -   we can add the numbers,
我们是可以把它们所含有的数字相加
and then we can get a number. There are different types in Excel as well
所得到的“和”将会是一个数字。 Excel里有 多种不同的“类型“
it's not just numbers. Suppose we have this in the cell
不仅仅只有数字这种类型而已。 假设在这单元格里的是
a string, a piece of text. We can calculate on text
一行字符。 我们也是可以 计算
as well.
字符的。
So what are the types here?
这些是属于什么类型呢？
We have again something that contains
相同地，如果我们用在公式里的是字符
a text and the result of the function
那么函数处理出来的
is a text. So these functions all
结果将会是文字。 因此，这些函数公式都有一个规律
take in the same values a number resulting in a number
就是数字产生数字
or text resulting in a text.
或者字符产生字符。
But there are also functions that can take in a certain type
但也有些函数，它们运算出来的结果
but return a different type. Let's have a look at how that looks like.
和输入的参数是属于不同的“类型”。 让我们 看看那是什么样子的。
For instance if we are calculating with dates...
举例来说，如果我们在计算日期
We have a date in our spreadsheet now and we can calculate with dates as well.
我们的电子表格里有一个日期数据，现在我们就行运算。
We've seen that in the past.
这是我们在之前的课程中教过的。
We could for instance calculate
例如，我们如果要计算
the month of A1, which would result in 1.
A1的月份，那么结果将会是 1。
So here you see an example of something that takes in
这个就是一个特殊的例子
a certain value, it takes in a container,
我们输入函数里的数据，可以被比喻成一个“容器”
something that contains a cell, containing a date,
该“容器”里包含了一个单元格，也包含离一个日期，
but it results in a number. So there
但运算结果得出的却是一个数字。 因此，
you take in a date, but you return a number. So sometimes the types of
你处理的是日期，但你得的却到数字。 所以我们说
inputs are different from the types of the output. They don't necessarily have
有时输入的类型与输出的类型是不一样的。 它们并不一定
to match.
要互相匹配的。
So now let's have a look at
好，现在让我们一起看看
the most complicated construction that we're going to look at
以下这个本周视频中
in these week's videos. It's still pretty basic I hope.
最为复杂的结构。 我希望它对大家来说仍是十分基础的。
Suppose we have a range we have 1,
假设我们在一个电子表格有1、2、3三个数字
2, 3 in a spreadsheet we can calculate on that. We know how to do that
以供我们运算。 这大家都应该知道怎么计算吧
so we can say something like the SUM() of
我们可以使用 SUM（）
A1 to A3
来计算从A1到A3的总和
which in this case is 6. So what are the types here?
这个例子中得到的答案是6。 那么，它们的类型是什么？
Let's start with 6 because that's super easy, 6 is a number,
让我们先看看6，这很简单，6是一个数字，
we know that. But what do we have here? We could say
大家都应该知道。 但是，我们这里有什麽？ 我们可以说，
we have three
我们有三个
number containers, three values that have a number.
数字的“容器”，三个数值都各含有一个数字。
But of course it doesn't necessarily have to be three.
但当然了，并不一定 有三个。
We can also say now we're summing until
我们也可以从A1一直加到
A5. Would that give the function a different type? It would have to add
A5为止。 那么函数的“类型”会因此改变吗？ 这个函数要把
another container here and one here.
这个“容器”加到这里，另一个也加到这里。
So we're not going to do that, this is not the way that we are going to write
我们并不会这样做，
this down.
这不是我们编程的方法
What we are saying here is we're summing over a list
而我们要做的是，把列表上的所有数字进行求和。
of numbers so the type, as I will write that down
大家会在我下个视频中看见
in subsequent videos is a list of numbers
这张列表中的数据
and the result of the function is a number.
以及函数所得的结果，它们的类型均为数字。
And this is very important to remember for the remainder of this week's videos,
这对于本周视频其余部分非常重要，请大家谨记。
that was the end of the typing secrets.
以上就是我们要了解的关于“类型”的小秘技了。